<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Fish(er)]]></title>
  <link href="http://ericpfisher.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ericpfisher.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-21T13:47:58-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ericpfisher.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Fisher]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boxen]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/04/21/boxen/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T09:01:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/04/21/boxen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before the weekend, I decided to poke around <a href="https://boxen.github.com/">Boxen</a> and see what all the fuss is about. I&rsquo;ve toyed around with Puppet, but struggled when it came to getting it working in a <em>pure</em> OS X environment, both agent and master (especially master). I had heard about Boxen when I first started investigating Puppet, but neglected to do enough research to find its true value: is it <em><em>the</em></em> OS X (master-less) Puppet!</p>

<p><em>Why Do I Need It?</em></p>

<p>Yeah, I had that question to. I thought, &ldquo;Hmm&hellip;I don&rsquo;t really manage Macs, and Puppet is for managing heterogenous groups of nodes (servers, computers), so it&rsquo;s probably not for me.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I was wrong.</p>

<h4>Overview</h4>

<p>Boxen is OS X&rsquo;s master-less Puppet. It&rsquo;s self-contained, meaning you can clone the <a href="https://github.com/boxen/our-boxen/">our-boxen</a> repository from Github, install Boxen, and run it. Mind you, it&rsquo;s going to be very bare-bones upon first run, but as you grow with your Mac, Boxen will be there every step of the way.</p>

<p>Boxen, like its Puppet cousin, works based upon the <em>state</em> you wish your machine to be in. Think about it this way:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Sublime Text should be installed.&rdquo;</em><br/>
<em>&ldquo;SSH should be activated and running.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>A lot of &ldquo;shoulds.&rdquo; That&rsquo;s how Boxen works. You include modules that reflect the state your unit should be in, and on each run, Boxen checks the current configuration against the desired state&hellip;and makes configuration changes to put the unit in the desired state. There are two parts that enforce the &ldquo;state&rdquo; for your Mac: Puppetfile and the manifest (e.g. site.pp).</p>

<p>The Puppetfile is a list of resources, telling Boxen where to look when downloading modules:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Puppetfile snippet</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="n">github</span> <span class="s2">&quot;ruby&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>        <span class="s2">&quot;7.3.0&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The &ldquo;github&rdquo; is a function declared earlier in the Puppetfile. It just takes the name of the module + it&rsquo;s module version and pulls the module data from Boxen&rsquo;s module list:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Puppetfile &#8220;github&#8221; method</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="c1"># Shortcut for a module from GitHub&#39;s boxen organization</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">github</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">args</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">options</span> <span class="o">||=</span> <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">args</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">last</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">is_a?</span> <span class="no">Hash</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">args</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">last</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">else</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="p">{}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">path</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">options</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">delete</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="ss">:path</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">mod</span> <span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:path</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">path</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">else</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">version</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">args</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">first</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">options</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="ss">:repo</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">||=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;boxen/puppet-</span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">mod</span> <span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">version</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="ss">:github_tarball</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">options</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="ss">:repo</span><span class="o">]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then, once you&rsquo;ve declared where to get your desired resources, you tell Boxen in the manifest (e.g. site.pp) that you want it to be included on this machine:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Boxen manifest include</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="kp">include</span> <span class="n">ruby</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>No extra punctuation needed. With those two things in place, Boxen will handle all the rest and get your computer configured the way you want.</p>

<h4>Gotcha No. 1</h4>

<p>Once Boxen was installed, I was all excited to try it out and install something I didn&rsquo;t have on my machine. The syntax for including modules in the Puppetfile looked very straight-forward. I just didn&rsquo;t know where people were getting their version numbers. To be honest, I&rsquo;m still not quite sure where to locate versions for modules, but I&rsquo;ve had the best luck using <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a> and searching for Boxen modules. The module info usually contains a version. That&rsquo;s what I used for my Vagrant module&hellip;</p>

<h4>Gotcha No. 2</h4>

<p>There&rsquo;s a <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/22352838/ruby-gem-install-json-fails-on-mavericks-and-xcode-5-1-unknown-argument-mul">compile bug</a> when running Boxen on OS X Mavericks:</p>

<p>To run it successfully while in the /opt/boxen/repo (and avoid FDE):</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Mavericks vs. XCode 5.1</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'><span class="nv">ARCHFLAGS</span><span class="o">=</span>-Wno-error<span class="o">=</span>unused-command-line-argument-hard-error-in-future ./script/boxen --no-fde
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Onward</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m excited to grow with Boxen and discover new ways to enhance my own workflow. Now, to keep this enthusiasm up&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Got Schooled]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/02/24/got-schooled/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T15:04:03-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/02/24/got-schooled</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I thought I was hot stuff going through Chris Pine&rsquo;s <a href="http://pragprog.com/book/ltp2/learn-to-program"><em>Learn To Program</em></a> when I blitzed through the first nine chapters no problem. The exercises were a good challenge, but didn&rsquo;t pose too much of a threat&hellip;</p>

<p>And then I got to chapter ten. In ten, Chris struck a cord with me when he challenges his readers to define his or her own <em>sort</em> method:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;like the Jedi who constructs his own lightsaber, you&rsquo;ll exhibit a greater mastery if you write your own sorting method.</p></blockquote>

<p>Challenge accepted! That was five days ago.</p>

<h3>Enter the Sorting Dragon</h3>

<p>I tried everything I could think of, but still struggled with ultimately keeping track of my data.  I found a great analogy someone posted about treating the elements of your array like playing cards (having &ldquo;sorted&rdquo;, &ldquo;unsorted&rdquo;, and &ldquo;active&rdquo; groups of elements), and think of solving the problem that way. That was a good starting point, but I was still struggling because I couldn&rsquo;t find a way to selectively remove elements from the unsorted array once I had added them to the sorted array.</p>

<p>So, I eventually broke down and checked Chris&#8217; solution at the end of the book. Our code was identical except for one key point of logic:</p>

<h5>Me:</h5>

<ol>
<li>Pop an element from the original array.</li>
<li>Add it to the sorted list.</li>
<li>Iterate through the remaining elements.

<ul>
<li>If there was an element smaller than what was already added, replace it and push the less-small element back into the unsorted pile.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Repeat (using array.each) until length of sorted array matched original array.</li>
</ol>


<h6>Chris:</h6>

<ol>
<li>Pop an element from the original array.</li>
<li>Assign it to a local variable. Create an empty &ldquo;unsorted&rdquo; array.</li>
<li>Iterate through the remaning elements.

<ul>
<li>If there was a smaller element than what was reference by the variable, replace it and push the less-small element to the &ldquo;unsorted&rdquo; array.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Repeat (using array.each) until the variable contains the smallest element from the original array.</li>
<li>Push that smallest element into the &ldquo;sorted&rdquo; array, and recursively pass the &ldquo;unsorted&rdquo; array to the sort method until the &ldquo;unsorted&rdquo;.length &lt;= 0.</li>
</ol>


<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Well, I have to give myself <em>some</em> credit. When I saw his answer, he and I were on the same page logic-wise. But, like a math problem, the devil is in the details. I was performing an action a bit too soon and hadn&rsquo;t separated my logic from my action: I was adding to the sorted list and <em>then</em> comparing instead of the other way around.</p>

<p>All in all, I think this was a very valuable lesson for me, that I&rsquo;m not as much an &ldquo;advanced beginner&rdquo; as I thought I was. I&rsquo;m going to try to swallow my pride (which was a bit hurt, I&rsquo;ll be honest), finish the exercises in the chapter, and keep learning.</p>

<p>No giving up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-18T08:40:55-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpfisher.github.io/blog/2014/02/18/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Thank You, Octopress</h3>

<p>Round of applause for Octopress for making this &ldquo;I-have-skill-and-want-to-maintain-my-own-blog-but-I-didn&rsquo;t-go-to-school-for-web-development&rdquo; thing so easy. You see that <em>Powered by Octopress</em> at the bottom of this page? Click it.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also really liking <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">Markdown</a> quite a bit. I ran through a quick Markdown <a href="www.markdowntutorial.com">tutorial</a> and within 30 minutes, I feel I have enough MD skill to write this post&hellip;so <strong>that&rsquo;s</strong> something.</p>

<p>On the subject of Markdown, I had no idea it was created by John Gruber of <a href="http://daringfireball.net"><em>The Daring Fireball</em></a> fame. I was even more surprised to learn that the creation of Markdown was greatly assisted by the late <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aaron_Swartz">Aaron Swartz</a>. Now that I know a tiny bit about the language and I&rsquo;ve witnessed first-hand how easy it is to use, it makes perfect sense something this simple and powerful would come from a pair like those two. Although, the English major in me is having a hard time not double-spacing after every sentence&hellip;damn you, soft break!</p>

<h3>WhyTF Am I Writing This???</h3>

<p>Yeah, I&rsquo;ve tried to start blogs before. I had a Xanga back in the day. I think it&rsquo;s still out there, actually.  I&rsquo;ve tried keeping a word processor document on my computer with various dates and thoughts. Always failed within a week. I&rsquo;m just not driven to write; I have to work for it.</p>

<p>So, <em>this</em> thing will (hopefully) be different. I was inspired by <a href="http://joshuakemp.blogspot.com"><em>Confessions of an Unlikely Developer</em></a>. Dude was a farrier (you can Google it, you have my blessing) and one day said, &ldquo;F*** it. I&rsquo;m going to be a developer.&rdquo;</p>

<p>No degree.<br/>
No overt technology background.<br/>
Three hours of study a day.<br/>
Attending regular coding meetups.<br/>
Practice + practice + more practice.</p>

<p>Eight months later and he&rsquo;s a Junior Developer (props to him for sure!).</p>

<p>Here I am with an overt technology background (I worked as a technician at Apple, dammit!), I&rsquo;ve built websites and scripts before, and I can&rsquo;t scrape together the time to hone in and make my work goal (to code for a living) a reality?! F*** that. (I still can&rsquo;t decide how candid I want to be on this thing, so bear with my censoring for now.)</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to use this blog to track my progress, catalog things I learn, and push myself to keep going. I love to learn, but I hate learning when I feel like it&rsquo;s going nowhere. This blog is to prove myself wrong. I&rsquo;m gonna learn me some Ruby.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>Obligatory First Code Snippet</span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Hello, World!&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
